<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<eml:eml xmlns:eml="https://eml.ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.2.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:stmml="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.2" packageId="edi.503.1" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.2.0  https://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.2.0/xsd/eml.xsd" system="edi">
  <access authSystem="https://pasta.edirepository.org/authentication" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
    <allow>
      <principal>uid=ccarey,o=EDI,dc=edirepository,dc=org</principal>
      <permission>all</permission>
    </allow>
    <allow>
      <principal>public</principal>
      <permission>read</permission>
    </allow>
  </access>
  <dataset>
    <title>Macrosystems EDDIE Module 4: Macro-Scale Feedbacks</title>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Cayelan</givenName>
        <givenName>C.</givenName>
        <surName>Carey</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Virginia Tech</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>Cayelan@vt.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8835-4476</userId>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Kaitlin</givenName>
        <givenName>J.</givenName>
        <surName>Farrell</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>University of Georgia</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>kfarrell@uga.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4709-7749</userId>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Alexandria</givenName>
        <givenName>G.</givenName>
        <surName>Hounshell</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Virginia Tech</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>alexgh@vt.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1616-9399</userId>
    </creator>
    <pubDate>2020-04-17</pubDate>
    <abstract>
      <para>
  Environmental phenomena are often driven by multiple factors that
  interact across space and over time. In freshwater lakes and
  reservoirs worldwide, carbon cycling and subsequent carbon dioxide
  (CO2) and methane (CH4) fluxes are changing due to local, regional,
  and continental drivers. In this module, students will learn how to
  set up a lake model and "force" the model with climate
  scenarios to test hypotheses about how local and global drivers will
  interact to promote or suppress greenhouse gas fluxes in different
  lakes. The overarching goal of this module is for students to explore
  new modeling and computing tools while learning fundamental concepts
  about how non-linear macrosystem-level phenomena (e.g., lake
  greenhouse gas fluxes) can occur through macro-scale feedbacks. The
  A-B-C structure of this module makes it flexible and adaptable to a
  range of student levels and course structures.
</para>
      <para>
  This dataset contains instructional materials and the files necessary
  to run the complete module. Readers are referred to the GLM science
  manual (Hipsey et al. 2014; 2019) for further details on model
  configuration.
</para>
    </abstract>
    <intellectualRights>
      <para>
  This information is released under the Creative Commons license -
  Attribution - CC BY (https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/).
  The consumer of these data ("Data User" herein) is required
  to cite it appropriately in any publication that results from its use.
  The Data User should realize that these data may be actively used by
  others for ongoing research and that coordination may be necessary to
  prevent duplicate publication. The Data User is urged to contact the
  authors of these data if any questions about methodology or results
  occur. Where appropriate, the Data User is encouraged to consider
  collaboration or co-authorship with the authors. The Data User should
  realize that misinterpretation of data may occur if used out of
  context of the original study. While substantial efforts are made to
  ensure the accuracy of data and associated documentation, complete
  accuracy of data sets cannot be guaranteed. All data are made
  available "as is." The Data User should be aware, however,
  that data are updated periodically and it is the responsibility of the
  Data User to check for new versions of the data. The data authors and
  the repository where these data were obtained shall not be liable for
  damages resulting from any use or misinterpretation of the data. Thank
  you.
</para>
    </intellectualRights>
    <coverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>The Department of Biological Sciences at Virginia Tech is located in Blacksburg, Virginia, USA</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-80.426228</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-80.424863</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>37.229596</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>37.22854</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>2019-04-01</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>2020-04-15</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <maintenance>
      <description>Completed</description>
    </maintenance>
    <contact>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Cayelan</givenName>
        <givenName>C.</givenName>
        <surName>Carey</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Virginia Tech</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>Cayelan@vt.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8835-4476</userId>
    </contact>
    <methods>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <para>
  MODULE DEVELOPMENT AND TESTING Module teaching materials were
  developed by C.C. Carey, K.J. Farrell, and A.G. Hounshell to provide
  instructors of undergraduate ecology courses with a ready-to-use,
  adaptable module that could be implemented in a 3-4 hour time period.
</para>
          <para>
  As the fourth module within the suite of Macrosystems EDDIE
  (www.macrosystemseddie.org) teaching materials, this module was
  developed to teach students fundamental concepts about macrosystems
  ecology, and how a macrosystems approach can be used to understand how
  lakes are affected by drivers that operate on multiple, interconnected
  temporal and spatial scales. As a secondary goal, Macrosystems EDDIE
  modules introduce students to advanced computational tools as a way to
  manage, analyze, visualize, and interpret high-frequency and long-term
  ecological data sets.
</para>
          <para>
  The specific student learning goals for this module are that by the
  end of the module, students will be able to: - Understand the concepts
  of macrosystems ecology and macro-scale feedbacks, and how different
  ecological processes can interact at local, regional, and continental
  scales. - Simulate greenhouse gas fluxes in multiple lakes using
  ecosystem models of lake water chemistry set up with
  publicly-available high-frequency sensor datasets (Activity A). - Test
  the effects of a climate scenario on the different lake models and
  examine how the timing and magnitude of greenhouse gas fluxes change
  with climate warming (Activity B). - Examine how local conditions may
  alter the timing and magnitude of greenhouse gas fluxes from lakes to
  affect global climate change (Activity C). - Predict how lake
  greenhouse gas fluxes may both respond to and amplify changing
  climate. - The module was assessed by volunteer faculty testers during
  the 2018-2019 academic year. Faculty testers provided feedback that
  was used to update and optimize teaching materials. Carey, Farrell,
  and Hounshell also used student pre- and post-module assessment
  questions to gauge effectiveness of teaching materials for achieving
  module learning goals. Pedagogical specialists with the Science
  Education Resource Center at Carleton College assisted with assessment
  development and implementation.
</para>
          <para>
  UNDERLYING MODEL DATA The module uses the General Lake Model (GLM;
  Hipsey et al. 2014), an open-source hydrodynamic simulation model, to
  simulate lake temperatures and other physical limnology metrics over
  the model time period. GLM in this module (version 2.2.0rc5) uses the
  'GLMr' and 'glmtools' packages (Read and Winslow 2016, Winslow and
  Read 2016), which allow the GLM model to be run and output analyzed
  through the R statistical environment. Calibrated models were set up
  for four lakes that are part of either the United States National
  Ecological Observatory Network (NEON; www.neonscience.org) or the
  Global Lakes Ecological Observatory Network (GLEON; http://gleon.org).
  The four lakes are Falling Creek Reservoir (Virginia, USA), Lake
  Mendota (Wisconsin, USA), Lake Sunapee (New Hampshire, USA), and
  Toolik Lake (Alaska, USA), which encompass a range of geographic
  location, trophic state, mixing regime, and watershed land use. The
  model representation of each lake has been simplified in multiple ways
  for the purpose of teaching this module: for example, lakes with
  multiple surface inflows were simplified to one inflow in the model.
</para>
          <para>
  Within the module, lake configuration files (glm2.nml) have been
  coarsely calibrated for each lake. Meteorological driver data
  (met_hourly.csv) for each lake were compiled at an hourly time step
  from the North American Land Data Assimilation System (NLDAS-2;
  Cosgrove et al. 2003) and include air temperature, short and long wave
  radiation, relative humidity, wind speed, and precipitation (rain and
  snow). For lakes that include a substantial surface inflow, an inflow
  file (inflow.csv) is included, which includes discharge volume, water
  temperature, and inflow salt concentration at a daily timestep. For
  lakes with a surface outflow, each lake model also includes a surface
  outflow file (outflow.csv) that is estimated based on inflows to
  maintain lake volume. Climate scenarios simulated +2oC, +4oC, and +6oC
  warming scenarios by increasing observed surface air temperature from
  2013-2014 by +2oC (met_hourly_plus2.csv), +4oC (met_hourly_plus4.csv),
  and +6oC (met_hourly_plus6.csv), respectively for each of the 4 lake.
</para>
          <para>
  For more information, we refer users to the website and publications
  listed below.
</para>
          <para>
  WEBSITE &amp;amp; PUBLICATIONS Carey, C.C., K.J. Farrell, and A.G.
  Hounshell. 15 April 2020. Macrosystems EDDIE: Macro-scale feedbacks.
  Macrosystems EDDIE Module 4, Version 1.
  http://module4.macrosystemseddie.org.
</para>
          <para>
  Farrell, K.J., &amp;amp; C.C. Carey. 2018. Power, pitfalls, and potential
  for integrating computational literacy into undergraduate ecology
  courses. Ecology and Evolution 8: 7744-7751. DOI: 10.1002/ece3.4363
</para>
          <para>
  Carey, C. C. and Gougis, R. D. 2017. Simulation modeling of lakes in
  undergraduate and graduate classrooms increases comprehension of
  climate change concepts and interest in computational tools. Journal
  of Science Education and Technology 26: 1-11. DOI:
  10.1007/s10956-016-9644-2
</para>
          <para>
  NOTES AND COMMENTS Cosgrove, B. A., Lohmann, D., Mitchell, K. E.,
  Houser, P. R., Wood, E. F., Schaake, J. C., Robock A., Marshall, C.,
  Sheffield, J., Duan, Q., Luo, L., Higgins, R. W., Pinker, R. T.,
  Tarpley, J. D., &amp;amp; Meng, J. (2003). Real-time and retrospective
  forcing in the North American Land Data Assimilation System (NLDAS)
  project. Journal of Geophysical Research: Atmospheres, 108(D22).
</para>
          <para>
  Hipsey, M. R., L.C. Bruce, and D.P. Hamilton. 2014. GLM- General Lake
  Model: Model overview and user information. AED Report #26, The
  University of Western Australia, Perth, Australia. 42 pp. Available:
  http://aed.see.uwa.edu.au/research/models/GLM/
</para>
          <para>
  Hipsey, M.R., Bruce, L.C., Boon, C., Busch, B., Carey, C.C., Hamilton,
  D.P., Hanson, P.C., Read, J.S., De Sousa, E., Weber, M., Winslow,
  L.A., 2019. A General Lake Model (GLM 3.0) for linking with
  high-frequency sensor data from the Global Lake Ecological Observatory
  Network (GLEON). Geosci. Model Dev. 12, 473-523.
  https://doi.org/10.5194/gmd-12-473-2019
</para>
          <para>
  Read, J.S., and L.A. Winslow. 2016. glmtools R package v.0.14.6.
  Available: https://github.com/USGS-R/glmtools
</para>
          <para>
  Winslow, L.A., and J.S. Read. 2016. GLMr R package v.3.1.15 and GLMr R
  package default files. GLMr: A General Lake Model (GLM) base package.
  DOI: 10.5281/zenodo.595574
</para>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
    </methods>
    <project>
      <title>A macrosystems science training program: developing undergraduates' simulation modeling, distributed computing, and collaborative skills</title>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Cayelan</givenName>
          <givenName>C.</givenName>
          <surName>Carey</surName>
        </individualName>
        <organizationName>Virginia Tech</organizationName>
        <electronicMailAddress>Cayelan@vt.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8835-4476</userId>
        <role>Principal Investigator</role>
      </personnel>
      <funding>National Science Foundation EF 1702506</funding>
    </project>
    <otherEntity>
      <entityName>instructor_materials</entityName>
      <entityDescription>This zip folder contains materials for instructors to teach the Macrosystems EDDIE 
                                 module in their classroom. See README file for file types and descriptions</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>instructor_materials.zip</objectName>
        <size unit="bytes">5822357</size>
        <authentication method="MD5">06079e6b66af055ee094bd94cd72a6b0</authentication>
        <dataFormat>
          <externallyDefinedFormat>
            <formatName>unknown</formatName>
          </externallyDefinedFormat>
        </dataFormat>
      </physical>
      <entityType>unknown</entityType>
    </otherEntity>
    <otherEntity>
      <entityName>macroscale_feedbacks</entityName>
      <entityDescription>This zip folder contains materials for students to implement the Macrosystems EDDIE 
                                 module in RStudio. See README file for file types and descriptions</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>macroscale_feedbacks.zip</objectName>
        <size unit="bytes">2391578</size>
        <authentication method="MD5">5ad7ff84a110505ccf4f16cd18796d6f</authentication>
        <dataFormat>
          <externallyDefinedFormat>
            <formatName>unknown</formatName>
          </externallyDefinedFormat>
        </dataFormat>
      </physical>
      <entityType>unknown</entityType>
    </otherEntity>
  </dataset>
</eml:eml>
